Society of Bibliophiles; Records apap179
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Society of Bibliophiles Records
1966-2002
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
The Society of Bibliophiles (Albany, N.Y.)
apap179
1.8 cubic ft.
From its formation in 1966 in Albany, New York, the Society of Bibliophiles aimed to encourage and foster a love of books along with an appreciation for the art of bookmaking. The Society of Bibliophiles arranged trips to various lectures and exhibits both within and outside of the Albany area, and arranged meetings and events at which books were the central focus. The collection consists of records produced between 1966 and 2002, and includes newsletters and announcements, organizational documents, materials from various sites visited and events, information about booksellers and bookbinders, as well as a number of other general administrative documents.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
Lorre Smith (secretary) of the Society of Bibliophiles donated all items in the collection to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives in 2004.
Biographical Sketch
The first meeting of the Society of Bibliophiles of Albany, NY was held on September 27, 1966, at which time the group adopted its name, elected a steering committee, and planned for future meetings and events. As chief organizers of this meeting, Walter A. Frankel and David L. Mitchell continued to head the society into the early 1970s, at which point Harriet Dyer Adams officially assumed the position of president until 1976. A formal constitution was established during the mid-1970s, describing procedures for electing officers and holding meetings, which were subsequently used in nominating Wayne Somers as the society’s next president in 1977. The Society of Bibliophiles arranged and attended meetings and lectures pertaining to book collecting, papermaking, book binding, as well as various authors and books. The group also began its annual tradition of a year-end Wayzegoose party in 1970, at which members gather for dinner and discussion of books.
Presidents of the society and the approximate dates of their terms are as follows: Harriet Dyer Adams (1970-1976), Wayne Somers (1977-1980), Sydney Ross (1981-1982), Arnold Elkind (1983-1984), Bruce Northrup (1985-1987), Ellen Fladger (1988-1991), Christine Bain (1992, 1994-2001), and Michael Aikey (1993).
Scope and Contents
The records of the Society of Bibliophiles of Albany, NY document the group’s activities from 1966-2002 (please note that these dates are non-inclusive). These activities, which reflect the society’s commitment to furthering the interests of book lovers (as noted in its constitution), include meetings, talks and lectures, trips to exhibits and bookstores/auctions, as well as tours of libraries and other book-related facilities.
The Society of Bibliophiles collection is divided into two series: Administrative and Subject Folders. The Administrative series contains general administrative documents generated and accumulated by the society during its regular activities. This series contains a file containing records for every year from 1966 to 1991, as well as for 2001-2002. Reflecting a change in the society’s recordkeeping processes, the Subject Folder series consists of folders referring to specific processes or types of records, including announcements, member materials, newsletters, and clippings. This series contain records dating from 1967 to 2002, although the bulk of the material falls between 1991 and 2000.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1 - Administrative, 1966-1991, 2000-2002, Undated
Series 2 - Subject Folders, 1967-2002, Undated
Series 1 is arranged chronologically while Series 2 is arranged alphabetically.
Literature; Book Clubs (Discussion Groups)--New York (State)--Albany; Book Collecting; Bookbinders; Booksellers and Bookselling; Papermaking; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence; Directories; Newsletters; Adams, Harriet Dryer; Bain, Christine A.; The Society of Bibliophiles (Albany, N.Y.)
- Administrative, 1966-1991; 2000-2002; Undated; 1; 0.75 cubic ft.
  Scope and Contents
  This series is arranged chronologically.
  The administrative series contains one folder for each year listed above. This series contains records that reflect the Society of Bibliophiles’ regular activities in the form of meeting announcements, correspondence, information about booksellers and bookbinders, information pertaining to organizing events and trips, and newspaper clippings. This chronological system of arrangement was used by the society from 1966 to 1991, and was adopted again in 2001 and 2002. Note that these dates are non-inclusive, as a number of documents are undated, but were placed into dated folders when they were originally filed.
  - Administrative, 1966; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 1)
  - Administrative, 1967; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 2)
  - Administrative, 1968; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 3)
  - Administrative, 1969; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 4)
  - Administrative, 1970; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 5)
  - Administrative, 1971 (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 6)
  - Administrative, 1972 (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 7)
  - Administrative, 1973; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 8)
  - Administrative, 1974; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 9)
  - Administrative, 1975; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 10)
  - Administrative, 1976; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 11)
  - Administrative, 1977; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 12)
  - Administrative, 1978; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 13)
  - Administrative, 1979; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 14)
  - Administrative, 1980; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 15)
  - Administrative, 1981; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 16)
  - Administrative, 1982; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 17)
  - Administrative, 1983; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 18)
  - Administrative, 1984; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 19)
  - Administrative, 1985; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 20)
  - Administrative, 1986; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 21)
  - Administrative, 1987; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 22)
  - Administrative, 1988; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 23)
  - Administrative, 1989 (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 24)
  - Administrative, 1990 (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 25)
  - Administrative, 1991 (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 26)
  - Administrative, 2000-2001; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 27)
  - Administrative, 2002; Undated (Box 1 (1-Administrative), Folder 28)
- Subject Folders, 1967-2002; Undated; 2; 1.05 cubic ft.
  This series is arranged alphabetically.
  Although this series contains records dating from 1967 to 2002, the bulk of the material in this series occurs between 1991 and 2000. This series contains many of the same types of materials as the administrative series, but is arranged alphabetically by subject, rather than by year. Folders in this series include announcements, member directories, program planning, and bookseller and bookbinder information.
  - Addresses/Address Changes, 1994; Undated (Box 1 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 29)
  - Aho, Gary, 1986; Undated (Box 1 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 30)
  - Announcements, 1991 (Box 1 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 31)
  - Announcements, 1992 (Box 1 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 32)
  - Announcements, 1993 (Box 1 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 33)
  - Announcements, 1994 (Box 1 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 34)
  - Announcements, 1995 (Box 1 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 35)
  - Announcements, 1996; Undated (Box 1 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 36)
  - Announcements, 1997; Undated (Box 1 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 37)
  - Announcements, 1998; Undated (Box 1 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 38)
  - Announcements, 1999; Undated (Box 1 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 39)
  - Announcements, 2000; Undated (Box 1 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 40)
  - Attendance Lists, 1992-1993; 1995-1996; Undated (Box 1 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 41)
  - Awards Catalog and Book Award Lists, 1993-1994; 1999 (Box 1 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 42)
  - Bank Account Information, 1987-1988 (Box 1 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 43)
  - Binding Samples, Undated (Box 1 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 44)
  - Book Agents, 1993; 1995; Undated (Box 1 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 45)
  - Book Arts Publications and Practitioners, 1997-1999; Undated (Box 1 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 46)
  - Book Auctions, Fairs, and Sales, 1993; 1995-1996; Undated (Box 1 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 47)
  - Book Club and Book Dealer Mailings, 1988-1989; Undated (Box 1 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 48)
  - Book Notecards, Undated (Box 1 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 49)
  - Books and Articles about Books and Book Collecting, 1995; 1997-1999; Undated (Box 2 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 1)
  - Bookseller and Book Dealer Information, 1983-1989; Undated (Box 2 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 2)
  - Booksellers Online, 1992-1993; Undated (Box 2 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 3)
  - Bookstores and Book Dealer Information, 1990-1992; 1995-1996; Undated (Box 2 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 4)
  - Bylaws/Constitution, 1985; Undated (Box 2 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 5)
  - Center for the Book, 1998 (Box 2 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 6)
  - Computer Programs for Book Inventories, 1990; Undated (Box 2 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 7)
  - Cookbooks, 1996; Undated (Box 2 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 8)
  - Copying Rates (Office Max), Undated (Box 2 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 9)
  - Correspondence (General), 1992-1993; 1995; 1997-2000; Undated (Box 2 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 10)
  - Dues Notices, 1979; 1983; Undated (Box 2 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 11)
  - Exhibits, 1994-1995 (Box 2 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 12)
  - History/Founders Information, 1984; Undated (Box 2 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 13)
  - Media Contacts, Publicity, 1994; 1998-2001; Undated (Box 2 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 14)
  - Meeting Place Information, 1992-1993; 1996; 1998; 2000; Undated (Box 2 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 15)
  - Member Interests Lists, Undated (Box 2 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 16)
  - Member Lists, 1977-1983; 1987; Undated (Box 2 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 17)
  - Member Lists, 1993; 1995; 2002; Undated (Box 2 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 18)
  - Membership Application Forms (Blank), 1983; 1987; Undated (Box 2 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 19)
  - Membership Application Forms (Blank), 2000; Undated (Box 2 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 20)
  - Membership Application Forms (Completed), 2000-2001 (Box 2 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 21)
  - Membership Directories, 1991-1995; 1997-2000; Undated (Box 2 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 22)
  - Membership Renewal Form and Sample Letter, 1995 (Box 3 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 1)
  - Mystery Book Information, 1991; 1994; 1996; Undated (Box 3 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 2)
  - New Librarians Reception, 1977; Undated (Box 3 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 3)
  - News Clippings Used for Newsletters, 1984-1989; 1991; Undated (Box 3 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 4)
  - Newsletters, 2001; Undated (Box 3 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 5)
  - Notes, Undated (Box 3 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 6)
  - Obituaries, 1993 (Box 3 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 7)
  - Officers during Bain Presidency, 1993; Undated (Box 3 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 8)
  - Poetry, 1999 (Box 3 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 9)
  - Printing and Graphics, 1993 (Box 3 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 10)
  - Program Planning, 1977-1983; Undated (Box 3 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 11)
  - Questionnaires, 1993; 1995; Undated (Box 3 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 12)
  - Reimbursements Due, 1998-2000; Undated (Box 3 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 13)
  - Society of Bibliophiles Brochures, Undated (Box 3 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 14)
  - Speaker and Program Planning Materials, 1980-1981; 1983-1984; 1986-1988; 1990; Undated (Box 3 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 15)
  - Stationery, 1972; Undated (Box 3 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 16)
  - Tax Status Information, Undated (Box 3 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 17)
  - Treasurer's Ledger, 1967-1976 (Box 3 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 18)
  - Treasurer's Reports, 1991-1993; 1995; 1998-1999; Undated (Box 3 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 19)
  - Undated Documents (Box 3 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 20)
  - Wayzegoose History, 1970; Undated (Box 3 (2-Subject Folders), Folder 21)